All right. So in this video we are going
to talk about what programming is. Um
since JavaScript is a programming
language it's important to understand
what programming is. So when you think
about a computer the way a computer
works is it uses ones and zeros to
communicate. It's just electrical
impulses. So there's either an on signal
or an off signal and then together you
can string those together to create
messages and complex pieces of
information. If you think like Morse
code, you can tap out a message in Morse
code. So, three short taps and then
three long taps and then three short
taps comes out to SOS and that's how you
would send a message for help. Um, and
that was how you could communicate in
Morse code. So, using just two signals,
a short signal and a long signal, you
could communicate in Morse code. So,
computers communicate using ones and
zeros. So, two different types of
messages, either an on or an off. Uh
this next slide um is a slide that shows
a message in binary. I do not speak
binary. Maybe one of you is really
really smart and you speak binary. Um
and you might know what this says. I had
to use a translator. But when I created
it, this in binary is hello world. So
it's not super efficient to have humans
write ones and zeros for a computer. Um,
so humans over the years we've developed
ways to communicate with a computer that
is not directly ones and zeros. So we
take human readable text and we
transform it into the ones and zeros
that the computer understands.
So on the next slide is how you would
write hello world in an assembly
language. So probably looks a little
intimidating. I hope it looks a little
intimidating. It's intimidating to me.
Um, but at the bottom it says hello
world. And so there is a little bit of
this that is human readable, but over
the years we've gotten even better at
this. So here is how you write hello
world in C++. It's a lot better, a lot
shorter, way briefer. Um, which is
great. Um, and I've got good news for
you. This is how you write it in
JavaScript. Just says hello world.
Console.log hello world. One line and
you are done. And that is why we like
JavaScript. So why study JavaScript?
Well, in a recent study done by Jet
Brains, they surveyed a whole bunch of
developers and they asked them what they
developed in in 2024. And so they just
recently published this in 2025. But as
you can see from this graph,
overwhelmingly JavaScript was the most
frequently used language in 2024. So if
you are going to learn a programming
language, JavaScript is the language to
use. And if you're still not convinced,
well, here's some things you can do with
it. Um, for web development, I'm going
to list off some, you know, little known
websites. You probably didn't know. You
know, they're built in JavaScript, like
google.com and YouTube.com and
Netflix.com. And I know you've probably
never heard of them, but all of those
are built in JavaScript. Um, if you want
to do mobile app development, um,
Facebook's mobile app was developed in
JavaScript. Instagram's mobile app was
developed in JavaScript. Discord was
developed in JavaScript. JavaScript can
do a lot of things. Some other things
that JavaScript can do include data
analytics, machine learning, can
automate financial processes and
accounting processes. Um, basically if
you want to do automation, JavaScript is
really good for that. Um, if you want to
scrape the web for information,
JavaScript can do that. And there's a
lot more. Basically, if you can dream
it, JavaScript can probably do it. Which
is why, um, there's a law that was
coined named Atwood's law. And it says
that any application that can be written
in JavaScript will eventually be written
in JavaScript. Um,
and so that is why I would study
JavaScript. Uh, welcome to the course.